<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-16T09:02:18-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Harshita Chadha</title><subtitle>MS in Computer Science student at George Washington University</subtitle><author><name>Harshita Chadha</name><email>harshitachadha@gwmail.gwu.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Modern Day Illuminati</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2022/06/moderndayilluminati/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern Day Illuminati" /><published>2022-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2022/06/moderndayilluminati</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2022/06/moderndayilluminati/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;View original presentation &lt;a href=&quot;/files/Modern Day Illuminati.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my senior year of undergraduate studies, I had the opportunity to delve into the intriguing world of media houses and their impact on society. Influenced by a previous presentation on human values and society during my high school years, I embarked on a thought-provoking journey to uncover the realities of present-day media. In this blog post, we will explore the notions of control, domination, and the influence wielded by media outlets, shedding light on their potential to shape major political events and public sentiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;News media, in theory, possesses immense potential to drive economic and social improvements, especially in developing countries and emerging economies. However, the harsh reality is often far from this ideal. Rather than serving the public and acting as truth-seekers in the face of power, many media outlets have become mere mouthpieces of the influential. Their actions are characterized by the repetition of unverified rumors, the perpetuation of discrimination against minorities, and the exacerbation of societal polarization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/illuminati.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences of such media behavior extend far beyond the boundaries of the media sector itself. By failing to live up to their responsibilities, media outlets contribute to the erosion of public trust and the distortion of public opinion. The immense power they wield in shaping narratives and influencing public sentiment cannot be overlooked. This modern-day Illuminati-like influence raises questions about the ethical responsibilities of media houses and their commitment to the principles of unbiased reporting and social welfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My presentation during the communications course shed light on the dark underbelly of present-day media houses. It served as a reminder that the media’s role in society is not to be taken lightly. As consumers of news, we must remain vigilant, question the motives behind media narratives, and demand transparency and accountability from those entrusted with delivering information. By doing so, we can foster a media landscape that genuinely serves the public interest, uplifts marginalized voices, and promotes a more informed and inclusive society.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Chadha</name><email>harshitachadha@gwmail.gwu.edu</email></author><category term="illuminati" /><category term="media" /><category term="false news" /><summary type="html">Non-Tech Post Unmasking the Modern Day Illuminati: Exploring the powerful influence of media houses, their failure to serve the public, and the detrimental impact on society.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ultimate horror series/movie list</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/horrormovielist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ultimate horror series/movie list" /><published>2021-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/horrormovielist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/horrormovielist/">&lt;p&gt;Lo and behold a creeptastic post because ‘tis the spooky season. Now that I have that out of my system, let’s get right down to it. Just so you know, bringing the list down to 10 was harder than anything that I’ve ever done. Now onto the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Haunting of Hill House&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/7OWv3N0f5x2slnM3ET/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Alt Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This series is my all time favourite and a permanent fixture on my Netflix continue to watch row. Although Hill House isn’t in your face scary, the narrative is beautifully woven together making the series a treat to watch. I wouldn’t do anyone the disservice of discussing the plot line hear. Instead I would sit in the corner and glare at you until you turn Netflix on and start watching this masterpiece. You’re welcome in advance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Conjuring part 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/8fQLDmrqXFVC0/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Alt Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being the proud host of my very own horror podcast, freakuency, there was no way I wouldn’t have stumbled across the likes of everyones favourite demonologists: Ed and Lorraine Warren. If you’ve heard about the Warrens and love all things scary, chances are that you’re already familiar with the conjuring Universe. These movies are based on real life cases that the Warrens investigated. If there’s one thing that makes a scary movie horrifying, it’s the based on a true story label and this franchise ticks that creepy little box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Grudge (Japanese Version)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/h9J9Mysy0X1FC/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Alt Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I saw this movie was when I was 12 years old. I was staying with my aunt and older cousin, and my mother had strictly forbade me from doing anything stupid like playing scary games or watching anything remotely horror. Keeping her warning in mind, I did the only logical thing: watched a Japanese horror movie with an unfamiliar title. The repercussions? Let’s just say that I couldn’t look at a flight of stairs without freaking out for weeks afterwards&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Haunted: Latin America + original&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/haunted.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Netflix original series has two parts. One based in the US and the other in Latin America. In the series, a bunch of people gather around and talk about their “real life” paranormal encounters. Most of the stories are unverified. I would take everything I see through a grain of salt. Real or not it does make for a fascinating binge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Buzzfeed unsolved supernatural (all seasons)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/3oeHLAHeEDz8C8mGjK/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Alt Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buzzfeed unsolved supernatural is a YouTube series wherein the two hosts Ryan and Shane visit “haunted locations” to conduct investigations into the question - “Are ghosts real?” Whether you are a believer, a skeptic or somewhere else on this spectrum, the series has got you covered. Its spooky ambience and mostly hilarious narrative make for a perfect weekend binge. The series is currently in its final season and honestly, I’m still trying to figure out how I’ll survive after it ends…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dec 2021 Update: Ryan and Shane have recently announced a new series “Ghost Files” all set to release of their channel- Watcher on YouTube. Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;House of Secrets, The Burari deaths&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/houseofsecrets.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a devout horror fan I grew up watching all sorts of gory movies and series. I am desensitised to this content to a degree that almost nothing phases me anymore. This series, however, proved me wrong. House of secrets is a Netflix documentary centred around the mass suicide debacle that took place in New Delhi (my city of residence) back in 2018. The series presents some real footage of the aftermath and the bizarre truth behind the incident as well as the media frenzy surrounding it. Despite having being aware of this incident, something about the portrayal of events in this documentary chills you to the core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Final Girls&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/finalgirls.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one’s a slasher with an actual storyline. It’s incidentally the only one of its genre to make the list. I watched this movie recently and honestly? I love the sound track the most. The story line is cool with a ton of extremely gruesome scenes thrown in to boot. The Final Girls is about a teenager who loses her mom in a car accident and a couple of years after this tragedy, finds herself trapped in a cult classic horror movie the mom starred in when she was younger. It ends on a cliffhanger though so proceed with caution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Shining&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/IwYXRW8IXRftS/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Alt Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need I say anything more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Annabelle Comes Home&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/9AILkQPZ2uTumtsfto/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Alt Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the name suggests this movie is about Annabelle and her home: the Warrens’ house in Monroe, Connecticut. This movie is like Mecca for horror lovers and features many of the famed cursed artefacts that find their home in the very real occult museum. The thought that these artefacts reside in the same dimension as me is enough to give me the creeps!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Ring&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/orU5I0JOQ83d9bHFZZ/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Alt Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ring chronicles the escapades of Samara- the well ghost. It can best be described as a result of the found footage craze in the horror movie industry during the 00s. In the ring universe, if you find Samara’s creepy little tape and watch it, she materialises in front of you through the screen and drags you into whatever little hole she crawled out of.  The GIF is a snippet of that tape. Don’t worry thought, this one’s not based on any real story. At least I think it isn’t…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I’m all out of recommendations. Proceed at your own risk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Chadha</name><email>harshitachadha@gwmail.gwu.edu</email></author><category term="movie recommendations" /><category term="horror" /><category term="halloween" /><summary type="html">Non-Tech Post Get ready for a spine-chilling journey with these top 10 creeptastic movies and series that will leave you sleeping with the lights on.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My GRE experience</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/greexperience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My GRE experience" /><published>2021-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/greexperience</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/greexperience/">&lt;p&gt;Applying to graduate schools is a daunting task. Not only are you planning to sell your soul to the devil for two years (according to multiple sub Reddits), you are also committing to an extremely rigorous application process. Now, while each facet of the application is equally important for an admit, arguably one of the most apparent roadblocks amongst these are the required standardised tests. Usually, most graduate programs across the globe require some standardised test scores. Since I plan to apply to schools in North America, for me these were the IELTS and the GRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having studied English for almost my entire life, the IELTS was a walk in the park; the GRE? Not so much. Now admittedly since I am from an engineering background, I did not find the quantitive part of the test difficult per-say. However, I did have problems getting past the 165 mark in the beginning. Perhaps due to the nature of the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I’ll go over the steps that I followed in order to achieve my score of 330 (162 V + 168 Q) with 4.5 in the analytical writing section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;General Overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graduate record examinations or the GRE is the most common standardised test that is a requirement for admissions in most non-business graduate programs. The test is typically 3.5 to 4.5 hours long depending upon your speed and constitutes six sections. The first section is analytical writing, it has two parts to it. Usually, in the first part the test taker elaborates their stance pertaining to a presented opinion. In the second task, the strength of a given line of argument is usually evaluated and points that could be stated to strengthen it further are mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next five sections are sort of a gamble. Depending upon your luck or personal opinion you either get 3 math/ quantitative and 2 verbal sections or get stuck with 3 verbal and 2 math/ quantitive sections. The extra third section, whether its verbal or quantitive, is experimental and your score there is not counted in the final result. The bad news here is that there is no way to tell which of the sections is the experimental one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How should one go about it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practice, practice, and more practice. During my 5 month long preparation, I gave countless practice tests, solved tons of question banks and attended many live question solving sessions. The key is to get used to the format of the test and train your brain to sit through a 4.5 hour fiasco without completely shutting down. This is because the concepts tested in both the verbal and quantitive sections are quite basic. The ETS guys don’t really want to test you on the expanse of your vocabulary or advanced algebra. They instead want to see how efficiently you apply basic concepts to solve seemingly impossible questions. That being said, having a basic and reasonably sized GRE vocabulary and the knowledge of some sneaky math tricks do help and save a ton of time. So where does this leave one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally started by taking in person classes from a renowned freelancer based in India ( Write to me at harshitaachadha@gmail.com for details). However I soon realised that taking the classic “Indian approach” to this might not be a great idea. So I spent the better part of a weekend looking for online resources and found a ton of helpful material (mostly free but some paid resources as well).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magoosh is an online platform that provides GRE self paced courses. They have a lot of helpful topic relevant videos but the most useful part of their platform is the math question bank. Its computer based, timed and overall a lot similar to the actual test format. Their plans, however, are towards the costlier side. If you’re looking to get your hands on the topic explanation videos but do not really want to subscribe, I’ve got you covered. I’ll link a folder below that houses the relevant resources. The said folder also has a ton of other useful material such as book pdfs, practice tests, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another online resource that turned out to be a life saver was gregmat’s material. I stumbled across Greg and his website while scouring through reddit and it was honestly the best thing that has happened to me all year. Greg has a ton of free online material both on his website and his YouTube channel. There’s tons of other useful material available with his premium subscription and before you guys run for the hills, its extremely affordable at only $5 a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another YouTube channel worth looking at is the tested tutor. The channel covers tons of tricky math topics and the verbal content is also quite great. Lastly and quite randomly, I stumbled across this Chinese website that, from what I could understand, is their version of reddit/ quora. In one of the forums, people post reading comprehension passages along with the answers and this can be a good practice for those of you looking for a hike in the verbal scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Specific Tips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
For analytical writing, I utilised the prompts in the practice tests that I gave. To get an idea about the structuring and the tentative components of the SA, I would recommend that you refer to gregmat’s video + the tested tutor’s video on this topic. Apart from that the only advice I can give is not neglecting this section. Its the first thing that you see and if it doesn’t go well on the test day, it may end up setting a grim tone for the rest of the sections. Also, the more used to it you are, the lesser would be the brain power it consumes on the test day.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
For the quantitive section, you should have timed practice sessions. A gregmat subscription gives you access to a math question bank with difficulty labels. If you have access, then start with the easy ones and time yourself. If you do not have this subscription and prefer referring to books instead, then also time yourself. It’s the way to go. Some of the topics that are the toughest and needed most reviewing on my part were Venn diagrams, work rates, and probability combinatronics mixed problems. I referred to the tested tutor&apos;s YouTube videos for these.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
For the verbal section, in sentence completion question more important than knowing the words is discerning the context in which the blank is presented. With practice you realise that more often than not, the answers end up being simple everyday words that we overlook because we fail to recognise the context. In the multiple word selection questions, very frequently the options given are presented in pairs (this happens quite often although not every time). If you are able to recognise the synonym pairs, the question becomes a cakewalk. Two words wouldn’t match at all and out of the other two pairs left, one would be totally tone deaf leaving the correct option exposed. This technique is explained in detail on gregmat’s YouTube channel in case my rendition was messed up. In the reading comprehension questions, the task is to extract the relevant information from the passage. You have to tear away the jargon to get to the main point. Again, I referred to gregmat’s video for better strategies.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Finally, for the vocabulary part, I think I memorised maybe 200 words specifically for the GRE. I am a firm believer in the fact that more important than mugging up words is to understand the question. However, I did have a vocabulary list and I’ll link that below along with the rest of the resources that I’ve mentioned.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s about it. If you found this blog post all over the pace, I apologise. I might still be quite close to the catastrophe to report on it objectively. Finally, I would like to remind you all that every person is unique with different strengths and weaknesses. This was my experience and you do not have to do everything I did to achieve your dream score. The only important thing is to find your pace and have fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;External Links - &lt;a href=&quot;https://magoosh.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Magoosh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/1tIFPRS_LC7XwLgR1hT5lnbp3-PPnjdgB&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;G Drive Resources&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gregmat.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gregmat’s website&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCktwzce9ncy_K78l1KBZkYQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gregmat’s YouTube Chanel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/TheTestedTutor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Tested Tutor’s YouTube Channel &lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/105122499&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Chinese Website&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1edWRDm1aoWx8_r1Q8M-d9eYhVAWgDxnK6-cuHgWSUXU/edit?usp=sharing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;My Vocab List&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Chadha</name><email>harshitachadha@gwmail.gwu.edu</email></author><category term="GRE" /><category term="IELTS" /><category term="experience" /><summary type="html">Non-Tech Post Navigating the GRE: Strategies, Resources, and Insights for Conquering the Graduate School Admission Test.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">And we named it freakuency</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/freakuencyintro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And we named it freakuency" /><published>2021-01-24T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-24T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/freakuencyintro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/freakuencyintro/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hiatus Notice - Following a thrilling and successful four-episode season, my co-host Shruti and I have made the difficult decision to put our podcast on hold. Life is taking us on a new adventure as we prepare to pursue graduate degrees in different continents. We want to express our deepest gratitude to all our listeners for their incredible support. Although we’re bidding farewell for now, we hope to return one day and reignite those spooky flames. Thank you, and stay tuned for future updates!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eatmy.news/2021/07/podcast-review-freakuency-summoning.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Podcast Review (07/2021)&lt;/a&gt; - featured on Eat my news&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eatmy.news/2021/09/podcast-review-freakuency-terror-traps.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Podcast Review (09/2021)&lt;/a&gt; - featured on Eat my news&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey there, fellow thrill-seekers! Prepare yourselves for a spine-chilling revelation in this captivating post. Drumroll, please Introducing my wickedly exciting project for 2021: my very own podcast!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the clock struck midnight in December 2020, a daring friend and I decided to unleash our inner eccentrics and embark on a podcasting adventure, delving into the bone-chilling realms that have captivated us for far too long. Brace yourselves, for this podcast, launching in April, shall become a sacred sanctuary for horror aficionados.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behold the frequency of the freaks! We’ve planned to grace your ears once every fortnight, with an extra monthly treat to keep you on the edge of your seat. In our regular episodes, we shall regale you with tales of supernatural phenomena, haunted locations, true crime cases, and urban legends, among an endless list of thrilling topics. But wait, there’s more! Our bonus episodes shall dive deep into the dark abyss of Reddit, scouring for the most bloodcurdling and gory stories to narrate. And when the stars align, we’ll sprinkle in our own eerie encounters to spice things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may be wondering how a science-minded soul like myself stumbled upon the supernatural labyrinth. Well, let me enlighten you. I grew up under the influence of a parent whose adoration for horror rivals that of Lorraine Warren herself. However, don’t mistake me for a true believer—I’m simply a masochistic enthusiast who enjoys sending shivers down my own spine, only to spend sleepless nights contemplating probabilities and jumping at the faintest of sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our episodes are crafted meticulously, ensuring they’re packed to the brim with bone-chilling content guaranteed to freeze you in terror. Clocking in at a tantalizing 20-25 minutes, they’ll leave you craving more. And fear not, for our podcast shall be available on all major streaming platforms, from Apple Podcasts to Buzzsprout and Spotify, granting you easy access to your darkest fears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my fearless friends, we’ve reached the end of this unapologetically self-promoting post. All I implore you to do is give our podcast a chance, see if our eerie vibes resonate with your frequency (pun intended!). For further bone-chilling details, venture forth to our official website &lt;a href=&quot;https://freakuencypodcast.wixsite.com/website&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until we meet again, stay haunted!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harshita C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. If you haven’t already guessed, the spine-tingling name of our podcast is none other than “Freakuency”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Chadha</name><email>harshitachadha@gwmail.gwu.edu</email></author><category term="podcast" /><category term="horror" /><category term="mystery" /><summary type="html">Non-Tech Post Introducing &quot;Freakuency&quot; - A bone-chilling podcast for horror lovers, filled with supernatural tales, true crime cases, and the darkest urban legends.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Your Next Big Weekend Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/projectguide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your Next Big Weekend Project" /><published>2021-01-23T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-23T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/projectguide</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2021/01/projectguide/">&lt;p&gt;Starting a new project can be quite challenging, especially when you’re struggling to come up with exciting ideas that truly ignite your enthusiasm. Luckily, I’ve always had a knack for brainstorming wild and wonderful concepts. Of course, being just one person, I can’t possibly pursue every single idea that pops into my head. That’s why I decided to write this article—to provide some much-needed inspiration for those of you who are currently facing a creative block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After much deliberation, I’ve managed to compile a list of five fantastic ideas that are bound to get your creative juices flowing. Who knows, one of these ideas might just become the perfect weekend project for you. So, without further ado, let’s dive right in and explore these exciting possibilities!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;h3&gt;The friend debt counter &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Now I know that money splitting apps are a dime a dozen on the app store and google play store alike but stay with me here a moment. What if instead of just splitting the funds, the app also keeps track of all the expenses you contribute when your friend group goes for an outing? I don’t know about you, but I have been in situations where I haven’t always had change to pay for my auto-rickshaw and one of my friends has swooped in to save the day. The app can help you keep track of all such little monetary nuances so that no one may call you a penny pincher the next time you decide to stop being the charity that serves cold coffees to aggrieved almost engineers. You could also maybe add a payment utility where all of your friends’ Paytm accounts can sync on one of the devices via some authentication and one account pays the establishment after collecting the split money from all accounts. Now that is stuff dreams are made of.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt; &lt;h3&gt;A hospital suggester &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Now since I plan to pursue my master’s in applied machine learning, it should come as no surprise that I decided to drag my personal interests into this otherwise generic list. I came up with this idea while watching one of the wonderfully informative (insert eye roll) news channels of our country. One of the age-old arguments used by media to slander any law enforcement agency is the time delay that takes place during transportation of the victim to the hospital. This issue sadly is not just an argument but in reality, many grievances turn to fatalities due to time delays. This project works to alleviate this latency. Real-time traffic data from google maps can be accessed to take care of the choice of the optimum route. The real work is to create and integrate a utility at the end of hospitals. Each hospital may have a central system that tracks the number of empty beds in the emergency room and using Bluetooth technology, the number of available doctors at that instant. Machine learning can then be applied to make optimum hospital selection where guaranteed and quick help to the victim is provided. If this entire technology is concentrated into an application, it can be of immense use in case of accidents or medical emergencies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt; &lt;h3&gt;A songwriter/Composer AI &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; This idea came to me while I was decorating my Christmas tree and was on the 3 millionth iteration of the same Christmas playlist. Since I have worked on creating AIs that can formulate fortunes/ horror stories when fed the right data, creating one that can come up with songs when fed a lyrical database shouldn’t be too difficult. The composer part may need some work. The composer section would require the model to be able to come up with a novel tune for the song that the lyricist part generates. Although it may sound pretty difficult, people have worked on this problem before. The article [here](https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2020/01/how-to-perform-automatic-music-generation/) may serve as a beginner’s introduction to creating a tune-generating AI. With both components of the project down, you can go to town with generating hundreds of songs of whatever genre you want. Just try not to get caught up in intellectual property lawsuits!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt; &lt;h3&gt;An app for quick CGPA reference &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Now I can’t speak for other colleges or universities, but the lack of centralized and reliable unofficial transcript generators for IPU students is the bane of my existence. Now, some online tools can be used to get semester wise results, but sadly they are pretty rudimentary with a very non-intuitive GUI. The CGPA reference app would need to create a central database by scraping the result data from the official IPU website which will not be that difficult because it is all publicly available as pdfs. The main part would be building an intuitive GUI which can serve as a quick reference for students when they are filling an internship application for the umpteenth time. One may also consider adding a CGPA converter that converts the CGPA from a 20.0 scale to a 4.0 one for all those poor souls who want to pursue higher education abroad.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt; &lt;h3&gt;A portofolio website &lt;/h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Seriously Harshita? This is what you’re thinking right now, isn’t it? I know. But trust me, however overused this project idea may be, it actually is quite beneficial in the long run. If you’re an engineer like me (well almost engineer anyway) then there may come a time when you have multiple projects that you have worked upon that really highlight your unique skillset. But since the resume you create should ideally be only one page long, you can’t include all of them on there. In such cases, it’s easier to have a website where you can showcase all your projects (maybe add cool demonstrations?). You don’t have to be into web development and create everything from scratch. If you’re a machine learning person like me (oh, how I hate CSS), you can make use of online tools like WordPress and Wix to create beautiful websites in a matter of hours. That is pretty neat in anyone’s book!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it! I am all out of ideas, for now anyway. If you have any follow up questions feel free to drop me an email.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Chadha</name><email>harshitachadha@gwmail.gwu.edu</email></author><category term="projects" /><category term="ideas" /><category term="inspiration" /><summary type="html">Tech Post Unleash your creativity with these five captivating project ideas, ranging from a friend debt counter app to an AI-powered songwriter, and find the perfect inspiration to kickstart your next weekend endeavor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Zoltar: The fortune telling AI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/10/ZoltarAI/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zoltar: The fortune telling AI" /><published>2020-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/10/ZoltarAI</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2020/10/ZoltarAI/">&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I’m excited to talk about one of my project - Zoltar the AI. Zoltar is an artificial conversation entity that has the potential for both simplicity and tremendous growth. I’ll provide a brief overview of the project, its dependencies, and walk you through the main concepts involved in creating a conversational AI. Then, based on the knowledge gained, I’ll explain the technical workings of this project in detail. To conclude, I’ll share a video demonstrating a conversation I had with Zoltar. So, let’s dive right in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fortune Teller project, known as Zoltar, is an AI powered by a custom-made dataset created from subreddits and New York Times Horoscope Data. For simplicity, I chose to utilize Python’s NLTK package, which is well-suited for cloud-based environments. This project is completely data-driven, meaning that more data leads to better results. Now, let’s start from the beginning to understand what exactly an AI is and how it can engage in conversations without explicit programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI is a sub-domain of data-driven computational practices that encompasses technologies like machine learning and deep learning. Back in 1955, Marvin Minsky and John McCarthy, both pioneers of Artificial Intelligence, defined it as any task that, if performed by a human, would be considered an application of intelligence. While traditional data-driven domains like machine learning focus on learning from data and making predictions, AI aims to replicate human behavior with notable success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fortune-telling AI uses data to comprehend sentence structure and the words provided. To delve deeper into its functioning, let’s familiarize ourselves with a few key terms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NLTK: Short for Natural Language Processing Toolkit, NLTK provides tools and functions for processing human language inputs. It is employed in various applications such as text classification, chatbots, sentiment analysis, and language translation. This is the main package used to build Zoltar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tokenization: Tokenization is the process of dividing large quantities of text into smaller parts called tokens. It consists of word and sentence tokenization.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Word Tokenization: This operation is accomplished using the word_tokenize() function of NLTK, which splits a sentence into individual words.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sentence Tokenization: The sent_tokenize() module is used to obtain a list of sentences from a paragraph, enabling us to analyze average words per sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stemming: Stemming is a process of linguistic normalization that reduces words to their root form or chops off derivational affixes. For instance, words like “connection,” “connected,” and “connecting” are reduced to the common word “connect.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;POS Tagging: POS tagging identifies the grammatical group of a given word and looks for relationships within the sentence, assigning a corresponding tag to each word.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lemmatization: Lemmatization reduces words to their base form, ensuring linguistically correct lemmas. It is usually more sophisticated than stemming, as it takes into account the context of the word. For example, “better” is lemmatized to “good.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Stop Words: Stop words are considered noise in text analysis. They are generic, repetitive, and irrelevant words that do not contribute significantly to the overall context. Removing stop words helps refine the data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a grasp of these fundamental concepts, let’s gain a technical overview of how Zoltar operates.The first step is to collect relevant data for training the model. I sourced New York Times fortune data from Kaggle and selected subreddits as data sources. Next, sentence and word lemmatization are performed to understand the data at its basic building units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this, irrelevant content such as stop words and punctuation marks are removed. Sentence vectorization is then used to group the stripped sentences into a bag-of-words model.The model is now ready to take user input and generate the most appropriate response by performing cosine similarity operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you have it! Your very own conversational AI, Zoltar, is now ready to hold stimulating conversations (well, not quite). To gain deeper insights into the project or try building it yourself, feel free to refer to the GitHub repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/harshitaachadha/Zoltar-The-fortune-telling-AI&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for the code and data. As a bonus, I recorded a conversation I had with Zoltar and added some creepy music to set the ambiance. Enjoy the video!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- blank line --&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;video_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video controls=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;/files/file.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- blank line --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about the terms or the project itself, don’t hesitate to reach out to me. I’m also open to discussing any improvements or additions you may have in mind for Zoltar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name>Harshita Chadha</name><email>harshitachadha@gwmail.gwu.edu</email></author><category term="Natural Language Processing" /><category term="Fortune Teller" /><category term="NLTK" /><summary type="html">Tech Post Discover the fascinating world of Zoltar, an artificial conversation entity. This blog post provides an overview of its creation, the underlying concepts of conversational AI, and a technical glimpse into its working, complete with a captivating video conversation.</summary></entry></feed>